One commonly used image segmentation technique is k-means clustering.
有种常用的图像分割技术 叫 k 均值聚类
It's a machine learning technique that separates an image into segments by
这是种机器学习技术 能将图像分割成若干部分
clustering or grouping together data points that have similar traits.
方法是把具相似特征的数据点聚类或分组到一起
As an example, let's look at this image of oranges in a bowl.
以这张碗盛橙子图为例
If I asked k-means to break up this image into two different colors,
如果我让 k 均值将图片分成两种不同的颜色
it will give us an image that looks like this.
我们就会得到这样一张图像
The oranges and the lighter part of the table are all
橙子以及桌上较亮的部分
considered to be one cluster of orange points.
被视为一簇橙色的点
And the dark background and any part in shadow are clustered as dark brown data points.
黑暗的背景和所有阴影部分则被归为深褐色的数据点簇
But, we're getting ahead of ourselves,
不过我们讲得太远了
let's talk about how k-means clusters this data step by step.
还是先来讲 k 均值是怎么一步步聚类数据的吧
K-means is called an
我们称 k 均值为
unsupervised learning method which means you don't need to label data.
非监督学习方法 也就是说你无须使用标签数据
Instead, unsupervised learning aims to group and characterize unlabeled datasets.
相反 非监督学习旨在分组并刻画无标签数据集
And, in doing so, often identifies patterns and similarities in groups of data.
而这个过程中 非监督学习往往会识别出多组数据的模式和相似之处
So, you can give k-means a set of any unlabeled data,
所以你可以给 k 均值任意一个无标签数据集
like the pixel values in an image,
比如图像的像素值
and just tell it to break it into k clusters
然后让 k 均值将这个数据集分解成 k 簇
where k is a variable whose value you choose.
其中 k 是变量 你可以选择该变量的值
For the orange example,
对于这张橙子图
we chose a k = 2.
我们设 k = 2
And if we increased that to say,
如果我们增加这个值
k equals three or six,
假设 k 等于 3 或 6
we would get three or six different colored segments.
图像就会分成三个或六个颜色不同的部分
In this case, those segments divide
这个时候 这些部分
differently shaded parts of the oranges and the table.
会把橙子和桌子不同的阴影部分分开来
Let's go through a simple example in even more detail.
我们来看一个简单的例子 更具体地探讨 k 均值
Here's a small image just 34 by 34 pixels of a rainbow pattern.
这张图很小 只有 34 乘 34 像素 是彩虹的一部分
I'll use k-means to separate this image into three clusters based on color.
我要用 k 均值 根据颜色将这张图分为三簇
To start, we know that each pixel in this image has an associated RGB value.
首先 我们知道这张图里的每个像素都有一个 RGB 值
In fact, we can actually plot the value of each pixel as a data point in RGB color space.
事实上 我们可以将各像素值当作 RGB 颜色空间的数据点绘制出来
The axis are just values for R, G, and B.
这些轴分别对应 R、G 和 B 的值
And notice the values on this axis.
注意这些轴上的值
Here, the highest R, G,
这里最高的 R、G、B 值
and B values say,
假设接近白色
close to white will be at this top corner.
会在这上面的角落里
And if we turn this space,
如果我们转动一下这个空间
we can actually see that the points fall into natural color clusters.
就能发现这些点自然而然地按颜色聚类了
If I tell k-means to separate this image data into three clusters,
如果我让 k 均值将这些图像数据分成三簇
it will look at these pixel values and randomly guess
那么 k 均值就会观察这些像素值 随机猜测
three RGB points that partition the data into three clusters.
三个 RGB 点 将数据分成三簇
Let's call these points center point A, center point B,
我们将这三个点称为中心点 A、B 和 C
and center point C. It then assigns
然后 k 均值会进行赋值
every pixel value to a cluster based on its closest center point.
把各像素值赋给最近的中心点所在的簇
So all of these pixels on the left belong to cluster A.
所以在左边的所有这些像素都属于 A 簇
And these more to the right to cluster B.
靠近右边的则归入 B 簇
And these on the bottom,
底部的
to cluster C. And here,
则归入 C 簇
I divided each into a separately colored region.
这里我把三者标成颜色不同的区域
k-means then takes the actual average or mean of all the RGB values in each cluster.
然后 k 均值会分别取各簇所有 RGB 值的实际平均数 也就是均值
And these mean values become the updated values for each center point.
然后将三个中心点更新为相对应的均值
Let's go back a step and take one cluster as an example, Cluster A,
我们退一步来讲 以 A 簇为例
k-means looks at all the pixel values in this cluster and computes a mean RGB value.
k 均值会观察这个簇里的所有像素值 计算出其中所有 RGB 的平均值
Let's call that mean A.
就称为均值 A 吧
It then updates the position of the center point A to be this mean value.
然后 k 均值会更新中心点 A 的位置 换成这个平均值所处的位置
This is why I initially called these center points.
这就是我一开始将这些点称为中心点的原因了
They're supposed to be in the center of their cluster.
因为它们就该是所属簇的中心
And it does the same thing for cluster B and
k 均值会对 B 簇的中心点 B
center point B and cluster C and center point C,
和 C 簇的中心点 C 进行同样的处理
moving the guessed center points to the mean of their cluster values.
将之前猜测出来的中心点移动到簇均值的位置上
Then, this process repeats.
重复这个过程
New clusters are formed based on where they are in
根据调整后的新中心点
relation to these new adjusted center points.
形成新簇
And then, an updated mean is calculated from
然后再次计算簇均值 更新均值
these clusters and the center points are updated again.
随后再次更新中心点
So, there's a sort of pulling done by the data points to create new center points.
有点像是数据点会相互拉扯 从而形成新的中心点
This process repeats again and the center points will generally move
这个过程会不断重复
a smaller and smaller distance from their previous value after each iteration.
基本上 每次迭代后 中心点的移动幅度都会变小
The algorithm keeps repeating these steps until it
算法会不断重复这个步骤
converges and the convergence is defined by us.
直至收敛 而收敛程度是由我们定义的
It's usually after a number of iterations, say 10,
通常算法会在一定迭代次数后收敛 比如 10 次
or based on how much the center points move after each iteration.
或根据每次迭代后中心点的移动幅度来确定是否要收敛
If the center points move less than some small value, say,
如果中心点的移动幅度小于某个较小的值
one pixel during an iteration,
比如某次迭代时 移动幅度只有一像素
then the center points have converged and the algorithm is finished.
那么中心点就收敛了 算法会终止
The center points that arise at the end of this process should best separate the data.
最后得到的中心点便具有最佳的数据分类效果
Next, let's see how to do this clustering in code.
接下来 我们来看看怎么用代码实现聚类